[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty-nine]
[第三十九集]
Guangdong military government has approved it.
广东军政府已经批准了
Chen Jiongming's plan
陈炯明的方案
Cui Bei wants to organize Southwest University.
崔备要筹办西南大学
Entrust Zhang Shizhao and others.
委托章士钊等人
There are two of us as organizers.
还有我们两个人作为筹办员
Take charge of the preparation plan for going to Southwest University.
去负责西南大学的筹备方案
Zhang Shizhao, say it.
章士钊说呀
He said he wanted you.
他说 希望你呀
Go to Shanghai to meet him.
到上海去一趟与他见面
Then go to Guangzhou.
然后再去广州
Something happened suddenly and I had to think about it.
事情有些突然 我得想想
Besides, I have to consult Junman.
另外我也得跟君曼商量商量
Master Cai
蔡公
The reason why I invited you here
我之所以把你请来
I just want to discuss with you.
我就是想跟你商量
I sincerely hope you can be like me.
我真心希望你能够和我一样
The main business is still in Peking University
主业还是在北大
Look at the Song History class next semester.
你看 下学期的宋史课
Everything has been arranged for you.
都已经给你安排好
And I really hope
而且我真希望
The two of us can be together
我们两个人能够在一起
Put the new culture movement
把新文化运动
Make it more thorough.
再搞得更加彻底一些
Zhongfu, I don't approve of your going to Guangzhou either.
仲甫 我也不赞成你去广州
Where is not suitable for you?
那个地方不适合你
Why?
为什么
There are too many radicals in the south.
南方那边的激进人士太多了
You must go to extremes when you go there.
你去那边 肯定又要走极端的
I'll miss your learning.
会误你做学问的
Master Cai Shizhi
蔡公 适之
The country has come to this.
国家都到了这个地步了
Where else can it be?
哪里还能容得了
What knowledge am I going to do?
我去做什么学问呀
Master Cai
蔡公
About leaving Peking University.
关于离开北大的事情
I've made it clear to you.
我已经跟您说明白了
I've made up my mind. Please don't persuade me again.
我去意已决 请勿再劝
As for whether to go to Guangdong or not
至于是不是去广东
Let me think again.
容我再想想
be it so
好吧
行蔡大师
行蔡公 适之
Then leave now.
那告辞了
Are you really leaving Beijing?
你真的要离开北京啊
There are many factions in Beiyang government.
北洋政府内部派系林立
Has lost control of the whole country.
已经无法掌控全国了
Compared with the southern government, it is more dynamic.
两相比较 南方政府有活力
It also has appeal.
也有号召力
Now Dr. Sun Yat-sen
现在孙中山先生
Put the Chinese Revolutionary Party under his leadership
把他所领导的中华革命党
Has been reorganized into the Chinese Kuomintang.
已经改组为中国国民党了
And statute to consolidate the Republic.
并规约以巩固共和
Realize the Three People's Principles for the purpose.
实现三民主义为宗旨
If dr sun yat-sen
如果孙中山先生
Be able to control the southern government
能够控制南方政府
The Beiyang government will be abolished in the future.
将来势必会取消北洋政府
Unified China
统一中国
I think if I go to the south now
我想 要是现在去南方
There may be more opportunities.
可能机会更多一些
So are we going to move our family to the south?
那咱们要把家搬到南方去吗
I want to make an appointment with Zhang Shizhao first.
我想先应章士钊之约
Let's talk about it in Shanghai.
去上海谈谈再说
Besides, YannianQiaonian is going to France.
另外 延年乔年也要去法国了
I also want to see them off.
我也想去送送他们
I feel really sorry for the two children.
我就觉得真对不住两个孩子
The expenses for Bai Lan have been collected.
给白兰的费用凑齐了
Yannian and Qiaonian's are not enough.
延年和乔年的就不够了
No money went to France.
没有钱 到了法国
I'm really worried about something wrong with them.
我真担心他们出点什么问题
The two children are used to being independent.
这两个孩子自立惯了
Don't beat them.
难不倒他们
December 1969
一九六九年十二月
Hunan Day, December, 1919
（十九十九年十二月
December, 1919
十九十九年十二月
To rebel against warlord Zhang Jingyao
为反抗军阀张敬尧
The reactionary rule in Hunan
在湖南的反动统治
Mazedong led a campaign.
毛泽东领导发动了一场
A massive drive to spread tension.
声势浩大的驱张运动
18 December
十二月十八日
Mazedong led the delegation.
毛泽东率领驱张代表团
Forty people arrived in Beijing.
行四十人抵达北京
Expose Zhang Jingyao's crime of harming Hunan and abusing people.
揭露张敬尧祸湘虐民的罪行
Strive for the support of the national theory for the anti-Zhang movement
争取全国论对驱张运动的支持
This is the electricity to expose Zhang Jingyao's top ten crimes.
这是揭露张敬尧十大罪状的通电
Send it out right away.
马上把它发出去
This declaration of expulsion
这份驱张宣言
Print another 30 copies.
再多印出三十份
Send it to every newspaper immediately.
马上送给各个报社
come
来
This is what I just wrote.
这份是我刚刚写好的
For Jin Yunpeng, the government of the Republic of China.
要给民国政府靳云鹏的
Quzhang Chengwen
驱张呈文
Print fifteen copies.
印出十五份
I need it tomorrow afternoon.
明天下午就要用
good
好
Runzhi
润之
Look who's here.
你看谁来了
middle
仲
Nakasuke
仲解
Runzhi
润之
Don't sit up and take notice in March
刮自相看
sit up and take notice
别三月 刮目相看
This blink of an eye
这一转眼
President of civilian news agency
平民通讯社社长
A famous journalist in Ninetowns.
九城闻名的大记者
remarkable
不简单
Students, this is Zhong Jie.
同学们 这位是仲解同学
Mr. Shouchang invited him to visit everyone.
守常先生请他来看望大家了
welcome
欢迎
Hello, classmates.
同学们好
Mr. Shouchang asked Zhong Jie to bring us a truckload of charcoal.
守常先生让仲解给咱们带了一车炭
Help everyone to get it at the door.
大家帮忙去门口拿一下
Duishen
对沉
Slow down
慢点啊
come on
来来来
Warm up
暖和暖和来
come
来
I'm driving ducks to the shelves.
我呀 是赶鸭子上架
thank you
谢谢
Learn by doing.
边干一边学
But honestly, hand, I missed you guys so much.
但说实话手 我想死你们了
You can also see it.
你也看得到
I'm tied up at the moment.
我现在忙得分不开身
Have you been too busy with this?
等忙过这一呢
I'm going to see Mr. Shouchang.
我就去看守常先生
I have a lot to tell him.
我呀有一肚子话跟他讲呢
Mr. Shouchang often reads to us, too. How about you?
守常先生也经常跟我们念你呢
Runzhi
润之
I brought you a nice thing.
我给你带了一样好东西
Guess what this is
猜猜这是什么
Come and smell
来闻闻
Taste of home
家的味道
寿昌先生
守常先生
I asked Jenny to fry the spicy oil for you.
特地让师母给你炸的辣油
Afraid you're not enough.
怕你不够
Ah, specialized
专门啊
Blow up two cans at once.
一下子炸了两罐
This should be enough for you to eat.
这下应该够你吃了
Mr. Shouchang also said a word
守常先生还说了一句话
Runzhi will worry without Chili oil.
没有辣椒油润之必犯愁
This campaign is less energetic.
这驱张运动 就少了精神头
Thank Jenny for me.
替我谢谢师母
Thank you, Mr. Shouchang
谢谢守常先生
Not only Mr. Shouchang
不光守常先生
Mr. Zhongfu also praised you.
仲甫先生也表扬你们了
classmates
同学们
I brought it to everyone.
我给大家带来了
The latest issue of New Youth
最新的一期《新青年》
Let's have a look.
来大家看看
come
来
Come to you.
来你的
中富先生
仲甫先生
Specially in this issue of "New Youth"
特地在这期《新青年》上边
Wrote an article
写了一篇文章
To support your anti-Zhang movement
来支持你们的驱张运动
The title of this article is called
这篇文章的题冒就叫作
Welcome to Hunan People's Spirit
《欢迎湖南人底精神》
Let me read you a paragraph.
我给你们念上一段啊
The spirit we can't fight for.
我们奋斗不过的精神
Gradually in class one.
已渐渐在一班
Lovely and respectable young people.
可爱的可敬的青年人身上复活
I heard this kind of voice.
我听了这类声音
Great joy
欢喜极了
Almost shed tears.
几乎落下泪来
good
好
come
来
it suddenly occurs to me that
对了
Mr. Zhongfu has been in some trouble recently.
仲甫先生最近遇到了一些麻烦
Is he okay now?
他现在还好吧
中富先生
仲甫先生
I have gone from Beijing to Shanghai now.
现在已经从北京到上海去了
I have a hunch.
我有预感
He will do something soon.
他很快就会干出一番
Earth-shattering event
惊天动地的大事情
Great
太好了
I went to Shanghai this time.
这次我到上海
Be sure to visit him.
一定要去看望他
Now the whole city of Beijing
现在全北京城
Are talking about your campaign to drive Zhang.
都在议论你们的驱张运动
How's it going?
怎么样进展如何
Had some trouble.
遇到了一些麻烦
This Beiyang government is like a merry-go-round
这北洋政府像走马灯一样
Change prime minister
换总理
Now this Jin Yunpeng
现在这个靳云鹏
move in and out with wizardly elusiveness
神龙见首不见尾
I can't touch his tip.
我摸不着他的梢子
Let me give you an idea.
我给你出个主意吧
He is just behind the cotton beard.
他就佳在棉花胡后
He lives in Mianhua Hutong.
他就住在棉花胡同
Go to his house.
到他家去
Zhang's poison is evil to Hunan.
张毒祸湘 罪大恶极
Xiangmin is in dire straits.
湘民痛苦 水深火热
There is no hope that poison will not kill Hunan.
张毒不除 湖南无望
Zhang's poison is evil to Hunan.
张毒祸湘罪大恶极
Xiangmin is in dire straits.
湘民痛苦 水深火热
Zhang du bu Chu
张毒不除
Zhang's poison is evil to Hunan.
张毒祸湘罪大恶极
Xiangmin is in dire straits.
湘民痛苦 水深火热
There is no hope that poison will not kill Hunan.
张毒不除 湖南无望
Zhang's poison is evil to Hunan.
张毒祸湘罪大恶极
Xiangmin pain
湘民痛苦
Everybody!
各位各位
The Prime Minister is busy with official business today.
今日总理公务繁忙
I'll tell you if you have anything.
你们有什么事我会转告
Everybody!
各位各位
Hopeless Hunan
湖南无望
On behalf of all Hunan people
我们代表全体湖南群众
Ask Zhang Jingyao to be expelled from Hunan.
要求将张敬尧驱逐出湘
How did Zhang Jingyao offend you?
张敬尧怎么得罪你们了
Zhang's poison is evil to Hunan.
张毒祸湘罪大恶极
Xiangmin is in dire straits.
湘民痛苦 水深火热
This is our petition.
这是我们的请愿书
Please forward it to the Prime Minister for a look.
请您转交给总理过目
There is no hope that poison will not kill Hunan.
张毒不除 湖南无望
Adjutant Yu
余副官
Zhang Jingyao has a big crime.
张敬尧有大罪
The soldiers hurt the people.
纵兵殃民
Make farmers unable to cultivate and businesses unable to market.
使得农不能耕 商不能市
Sin one
其罪一
Financial congestion
金融枯塞
The second sin
其罪二
Public and private bankruptcy will be restored indefinitely.
公私破产 恢复无期
The third sin
其罪三
Letting people plant tobacco damage the national system.
勒民种烟毁伤国体
Laughing at the world's four sins
腾笑全球  其罪四
The destruction of education keeps students out of school.
破坏教育 使得学生无校可入
There is nothing to learn.
无学可求 其五
Assassination of citizens violates the criminal law.
暗杀公民身蹈刑律
The sixth sin
其罪六
So many crimes.
这么多罪状
What else do you want?
你们还有什么诉求
We ask the government
我们请政府
Immediately expel Zhang Jingyao from Hunan.
即刻将张敬尧驱逐出湘
There is no hope that poison will not kill Hunan.
张毒不除 湖南无望
I see. Rest assured, everyone.
我明白了 各位放心
I understand, everyone. Don't worry
我明自了 各位放心
I will certainly tell the Prime Minister your request.
我一定会把你们的诉求告诉总理
Okay, okay, okay.
好好好
Good school manager
校董好
Yannian is here
延年来啦
Manager Wang said you wanted to see me.
汪经理说您找我
Is something the matter？
有什么事吗
Boy, I find you're in a hurry.
这孩子 我发现你还挺着急
Come sit down and have a cup of tea.
来坐下 喝杯茶
good
好
come
来
Thank you, school manager.
谢谢校董
延年啊
延年啊
Today, we'll have a frank talk.
今天我们俩就开诚布公地聊一聊
good
好
Can I ask you two questions?
我问你两个问 可以吗
Uncle, say
叔叔 您说
Tell me what your ambition is.
你告诉我 你的志向是什么
I want to be a country that can serve.
我想成为一个能够报效国家
One who serves the people.
报效民众的人
How do you want to serve your country?
那你想怎么报效国家
For example, being the leader of the country.
比如说 做国家的领导人
Or overthrow the regime of this country.
或是把这个国家的政权推翻
Build another country.
再重新建立一个国家
No, uncle, none of this.
不 不是叔叔 这些都不是
I'm not interested in being an official
我对当官不感兴趣
I just hope that our country
我就是希望咱们的国家
Don't be controlled by foreigners.
不要被外国人控制
People are not bullied by officials.
民众不被当官的欺负
People can live a good life.
老百姓能过上好日子
Then form a mutual help and love.
再结成一个互助互爱
Such a harmonious big family.
和谐的这么一个大家庭
I am willing to fight for it.
我愿意为之而奋斗
How do you want to fight?
你想怎么奋斗
I am willing to die for my country.
我愿意为了国家而献身
Yannian, can you tell me
延年 你能告诉我
What do you mean by dedication?
你说的献身是什么意思吗
Is dedication.
献身就是
I am always willing to sacrifice myself for my country.
我随时愿意为国家牺牲自己
How can you think of sacrifice at an early age?
你小小年纪怎么能想到牺牲呢
Do you have to do this?
难道你非要如此不可吗
Uncle, I think in a country like ours
叔叔 我觉得在我们这样的国家
Want to realize such an ideal
想要实现这样的理想
There is no other way to choose.
没有别的路可以选
I ask you
我问你
Your relationship with Liu Mei
你和柳眉的关系
What do you want to do with it?
你想怎么处理
Actually, this question
其实这个问题
I have answered you just now.
我刚才已经回答您了
You answered me just now.
你刚才回答我了
Then you have to forgive your uncle Liu's stupidity.
那你得原谅你柳叔叔的愚钝了
I really don't understand.
我真的没有听懂
I told you just now.
我刚才跟您说了
I'm willing to
我愿意为了
For this country and its people.
这个国家和民众而献身
So I have no intention of starting a family.
所以我没有成家的打算
As a follower of anarchism
作为无政府主义的追随者
I don't advocate starting a family.
我不主张建立家庭
As an anarchist communist
作为无政府的共产主义者
I abide by the six noes.
我恪守六不主义
Don't fall in love or have personal relationships.
不谈恋爱 不作私交
It is also the proper meaning of it.
也是其中应有之义
Yannian
延年
There are many people advocating anarchism in China.
中国崇尚无政府主义的人很多
But which one is not married?
但是哪个不结婚
Which one doesn't fall in love
哪个不谈恋爱
Why do you want to go to this extreme?
你为什么要走这个极端呢
You know, Liu Mei, in order to follow you
你知道吗 柳眉为了追随你
She abandoned everything.
她抛弃了所有的一切
You think you're doing this
你觉得你这样做
Are you worthy of her?
你对得起她吗
uncle
叔叔
I know you came to see me about Liu Mei.
我知道您找我就是为了柳眉的事
So I must answer you honestly.
所以我必须诚实地回答您
I do this.
我这么做
It is also for Liu Mei's happiness.
也是为了柳眉的幸福考虑的
It is also from the lessons of our family for so many years.
也是从我们家这么多年的教训中
Make a decision
做出的决定
How do you say this?
你这个话怎么讲
My father Chen Duxiu
我父亲陈独秀
Is an existing lofty ideal.
就是一个既有远大理想
A revolutionary who wants to have a family.
又想要拥有家庭的革命者
But I think
可是我认为
In our disaster-stricken country
在我们这个灾难深重的国家
It's impossible to do both.
根本无法做到两者兼顾
I can't repeat the same mistakes.
前车之鉴 我不能重蹈覆辙
Your heart is here.
原来你的心结在这儿
Uncle, didn't you just ask me about my ambition?
叔叔 您刚才不是问我的志向吗
I can give you a definite answer now.
我现在可以明确地回答您
From small rural areas to cities.
从小到大 从农村到城市
I felt it personally.
我切身感受到了
Corruption in this country and suffering of the people
这个国家的腐败和民众的苦难
Now I'm determined to fight for
我现在决心要为了
The strength of the country and the happiness of the people
国家的强大和民众的幸福
Sacrifice everything
而牺一切
I can't do it both ways like some people do.
我做不到像有些人那样两头兼顾
So I have to sacrifice myself.
所以我只能牺牲自己
proceed without hesitation
义无反顾
I see./I got it.
我懂了
Sit down.
你坐下
As an elder, I admire your ambition very much
作为长辈 我非常钦佩你的志向
And I also firmly believe that
而具我也坚信
You will have an extraordinary life.
你一定会有一个非同凡响的人生
You and your father are made of special materials.
你和你的父亲都是特殊材料做的
I'm not.
我不是
Liu Mei is my daughter.
柳眉是我的女儿
I am responsible for her life.
她的人生我要负责任
Do you understand me when I say this?
我这么说你明白吗
clear
明白
So I don't agree.
所以 我不同意
She went to France to work and study with you.
她跟你去法国勤工俭学
She doesn't need work-study now.
她现在不需要勤工俭学
Now she needs to be in a famous foreign university.
她现在需要在国外名牌大学里
Read quietly.
安安静静地读书
Please forgive me.
请你谅解我
There's nothing I can do.
我这也是没有办法的办法
uncle
叔叔
Then what else do I need to do?
那我还需要做什么
What you need to do now
你现在需要做的
Just do nothing.
就是什么都别做
Everything goes with the flow.
一切都顺其自然
Don't hate me either.
你也不要记恨我
good
好
Come a little closer
再靠近一点
Help him with it.
帮他弄一下
good
好
Look at the camera.
看镜头啊
A little bit of the bride's veil.
新娘的头纱稍微弄一下
I'll do it.
我来弄吧
Okay, okay, okay.
好好好
Yannian, about my dad talking to you.
延年 我爸找你谈话的事
He told me everything.
他都跟我说了
And I know what you think.
我也清楚你的想法了
I can't accompany you to France.
我不能陪你去法国了
I don't know why recently.
最近我也不知道为什么
Memories are always one scene after another.
回忆总是一幕幕地
Appear in my mind
出现在我脑海里
Remember the first time we met?
还记得我们俩第一次见面吗
At Aurora School
在震旦学校
We had a fight.
咱们俩打了一架
It has been more than four years now.
到现在已经四年多了
We went from Shanghai to Beijing.
我们从上海到北京
From Beijing to Shanghai
北京到上海
I remember we had a frugal canteen together.
我记得我们一起办俭清食堂
Feed the lambs together
一起喂小羊
Yiqibao steamed bun
一起包包子
Let's play live drama together.
我们一起演活报剧
Down with Wang Jingxuan
打倒王敬轩
Together we make a puppet
我们一起做木偶
Go to prison and hand out leaflets on the street.
进监狱 发传单 上大街
I remember everything.
我都记得
How I want to stay in yesterday!
我多想时间就停留在昨天啊
But time can't stop
可是时间停不住的
I wish I didn't want to be here today.
我多想不要到今天
But it's still here today.
可是今天还是来了
Yannian, do you remember what I told you?
延年 你还记得我跟你说过的吗
How much I admire you!
我多么美慕你们啊
You can fly proudly and fly freely.
你们可以骄傲地飞 自由地飞
Rely on home
不靠家里
I wanted to fly with you.
我原本想和你们一起飞的
But today I found out.
可是到了今天我才发现
I can't fly high.
我飞不高了
I can't fly out either.
我也飞不出去了
I made a detour.
我绕了一圈
I went back to this cage.
我又绕回了这个牢笼
Do you remember what I told you
你还记得我跟你说的吗
Those three words are not in my dictionary.
我的字典里没有那三个字
But you're going to France soon.
但是你马上就要去法国了
I can't go with you
我不能陪你去
I want to say sorry.
我要说对不起
I see
我知道
I'm ugly and stupid.
我不好看 还很笨
I can't do anything you ask me to do well.
你让我做的事情我都做不好
But there is one thing.
可是有一件事情
I know I can't fool myself.
我知道我骗不了自己
It's me all the time
就是我时时刻刻
My heart is full of you.
心心念念的都是你
I just want to ask.
我就想问一句
On the road of your future life
在你未来的人生道路上
Without me
有没有我
done
好了
I see
我明白了
You're going to France
你要去法国了
I can't see you off.
我送不了你
Take care of yourself and have a safe trip.
你要多保重一路平安
I'm leaving
我走了
Time is like running water
光阴似流水
I'll be home from school after class.
不一会 课闭放学归
Let's think it over for a while.
我们仔细想一会
Today, I masturbate.
今天功课明自未
What the teacher said
老师讲的话
Have you ever violated it?
可曾有违背
Parents' expectations
父母望儿
We went all the way to Moluya.
我们一路莫律衙
Governing the country in the future
将来治国平天下
Depends on our generation.
全靠吾辈
Everybody work hard!
大家努力呀
classmates
同学们
See you tomorrow.
明天再会
I'm sorry
对不起
Boys and girls, put the boxes in the car first.
同学们你们先把箱子往车上放
Put it here first, put it here first
先搁这儿先搁这儿
Move someone else's first, move someone else's first
先搬别人的 先搬别人的
Let me help you with your suitcase.
我帮您提箱子
Male students help female students move.
男同学帮女同学搬一下啊
Put this on that.
这个放那个上
Yannian
延年
Qiaonian
乔年
Put all the luggage in the front.
把行李都放前面来
come on
来来来
I help you.
我帮你
Thank you, Shen
谢谢谢谢沉啊
Everybody, put your luggage in the front.
各位同学把行李放前边来
good
好
Students quickly put their luggage on the bus.
同学们赶紧把行李放到车上
Qiaonian
乔年
Sister, I'll do it. I'll do it.
姐姐 我来我来我来
Pack big luggage in the car.
大件行李往车上装啊
Slow down
缓一缓
It's really heavy
慢点啊
Your family didn't come.
你们家人没来啊
I didn't tell them. I don't think they know.
我没跟他们说他们应该不知道
Sister Lai
来姐姐
Give it to me.
来给我
Slow down sideways.
横着放 慢点啊
dad
爸
I auntie didn't come
我姨妈没来啊
Auntie is in Beijing without you.
没来你姨妈在北京
It's better not to come and cry.
不来也好 来了又哭哭啼啼的
What she asked me to bring you.
她让我给你们带的东西
What do you bring?
带的是什么
Let's see it on the boat.
到船上再看吧
I fried pumpkin seeds.
南瓜子 我炒的
Be confused
蝴了
It's a mess. It's your style of frying
是蝴了 是您炒的风格
I'm in a bad mood.
蝴大发了
Come on, this is enough for you to eat in France
行了 这些够你们吃到法国的了
come on
走吧
You take this.
来你拿这个
Take this, take this.
拿这个拿这个
It's ok.
没事儿
Give me this.
拿这个 给我
come on
走吧
Is everyone here?
都到齐了吗
time is up
时间到了
It's time for us to start.
咱们该出发了
[4 July 1927, Shanghai Longhua Police Headquarters Detention Center]
[1927年7月4日 上海龙华警备司令部看守所]
[6 June 1928, Shanghai Longhua Police Headquarters Detention Center]
[1928年6月6日 上海龙华警备司令部看守所]
[Chen Yannian, Alternate member of the 5th Central Committee Politburo of the Communist Party of China, revolutionary martyr. Arrested in Shanghai in 1927, he refused to kneel, and was hacked to death by the Kuomintang, aged 29.]
[陈延年，中国共产党第五届中央政治局候补委员，革命烈土。1927年在上海被捕，宁死不跪，被国民党反动派乱力砍死，时年29岁。]
[Chen Qiaonian, Member of the 5th Central Committee of the Communist Party of China, revolutionary martyr. Killed by the Kuomintang in Longhua, Shanghai in 1928, aged 26.]
[陈乔年，中国共产党第五届中央委员，革命烈土。1928年被国民党杀害于上海龙华，时年26岁。]
Recalling the past?
忆往昔呢
The Old House of Bai Wenwei of Hunan and Anhui Comrades Association
湘皖同志会柏文蔚的旧宅
vigorous
轰轰烈烈
No one here knows you better than you.
对这儿没有人比你更熟了
Still mountains and rivers
山河依旧
It's hard to be calm
心潮难平啊
Brother Hangyan would like to thank you for saving me.
行严兄要多谢你救我
Otherwise, I would still be in the picture.
要不然我现在还在圖之中呢
Zhongfu, why should I thank you?
仲甫 你我何须言谢
sit
坐
Zhongfu, I've already let the word out.
仲甫啊 我已经放话出去了
Zhang Shizhao is willing to be Chen Duxiu.
我章士钊愿意做陈独秀
Life-long free nurse listener
终身的免费护律听师
Afraid of you later.
怕是你以后
There are many places where I can be used.
用得着我的地方还多着呢
What do you mean?
什么意思
Free lawyer for life.
终身的免费的护律师
There are many places where you can still be used.
还用得着你的地方多着呢
You mean I still have to go in?
你这意思就是我还得进去呗
A slip of the tongue
失言失言
You don't have to be scared.
你不用吓
Maybe you hit it right.
你不用哑
No, in the future
没淮啊阿我以后
Really will be in and out of the lab many times.
真的会多次进出那个研究室
I hear you now have an obvious
听说你现在有了明显的
Marx and the tendency of Russian revolution.
马克思和俄国革命的倾向
Is it right to transform China?
是不是对改造中国
Have a new set of views.
有了一套新的看法
I'm still exploring.
我还在探索中
The Road of October Revolution
十月革命的道路
It really inspired me a lot.
确实给了我很大的启发
President Meng of Wuhan Wenhua College
武汉文华学院的孟校长啊
I've heard a lot about you, Chen Duxiu
久仰你陈独秀大名
I have asked you to give lectures in Hankou many times.
多次托我想请你去汉口讲学
Look, you just got out of prison.
你看你刚出狱不久
I finally came out again.
又好不容易出来一趟
Why don't you preach in the past?
要不过去布布道散散心
Yes, I'd like to go.
好 我愿前往
What a happy promise!
答应得真痛快啊
Okay, I'll tell you the next thing
好再跟你说下一个事
Things in Southwest University
西南大学的事
After Mr. Zhongshan founded the Kuomintang
中山先生成立了国民党之后
Guangdong government strongly advocates ideological and cultural education.
广东政府大力提倡思想文化教育
So let Chen Jiongming brew it for years.
这样呢就让陈炯明酿多年的
The proposal to set up Southwest University was passed.
要成立西南大学的提案得以通过
The military government also specializes in
军政府还专门
Allocate one million yuan for preparation.
拨款一百万元用以筹备
This Chen Jiongming adores you.
这个陈炯明对你崇拜有加
I want to dig you into Guangdong to educate him.
一心想挖你去广东给他办教育
Let me send you a telegram.
这不就让我给你发电报
You made an appointment here to talk about it.
约你到这儿来相谈此事
He is afraid that you will change.
他生怕你生变
And let me specially bring a letter of engagement.
还让我特意带来了聘金聘书
otherwise
要不
Let's go in and hold an engagement ceremony.
咱就进去举行一个受聘仪式吧
You don't ask me if I want to.
你这也不问我是否愿意
That's it.
就来这一套
You this
你这
Why don't you want to come to Shanghai?
你不愿意你到上海来干吗
And I also know
而我还知道
You sneaked out.
你是偷看跑出来的
Coming
来了
Hello, Jenny
师母 您好
Is sir at home?
先生在家吗
not be in
不在
At the invitation of Mr. Zhang Tuzhao
他应章土钊先生请
At the invitation of Mr Zhang Zhao.
他应章钊先生请
I went to Shanghai on business and haven't come back yet.
去上海办事了 还没回来
I have been ordered to say hello to my husband.
我是奉命来给先生问好的
Nothing else.
没什么别的事
excuse me
打扰了
good-bye
慢走
Shi mu Liu bu
师母留步
Fellow students
各位同学
For more than half a year
这半年多来
The biggest change in China
中国最大的变化
There is nothing better than the wisdom of the people and the prosperity of the people.
莫过于民智大开 民气大盛
People are up.
民众起来了
Put forward the requirements of transforming society.
提出了改造社会的要求
I personally think
我个人认为
This is the greatest achievement of the May 4th Movement.
这是五四运动最大的成果
good
好
What kind of requirements should social transformation meet?
社会改造要达到什么样的要求
Everyone is very concerned about this problem.
大家都很关心这个问题
I spent 90 days in prison.
我呢 坐了九十天的大牢
Have some ideas about this problem.
对这个问题有了一些
Different ideas from the past
与以往不同的想法
Today, I will talk about it with you.
今天我说出来跟大家共同探讨
Social transformation
社会改造
To break the system of class.
要打破阶级的制度
Implement civilian socialism.
实行平民社会主义
Everyone should not have vanity.
人人都不要有虚荣心
Break the system of inheritance
打破承的制度
It is necessary to carry out joint labor.
要实行共同劳动工作
Let unproductive pain enjoy productive enjoyment.
不使无产的痛苦 有产的安享
To break the legacy system.
要打破遗产的制度
Don't let the land pass on privately.
不使土地私人传留享有
Communism that should be classified as society
应归为社会的共产
Those who don't farm should not enjoy the right to farm.
不种田的人不应该享有田地的权利
This is what Marx said.
这就是马克思说的
To eliminate the private property system.
要消灭私有财产制
Okay, okay, okay.
好好好
Such social transformation requires us to
这样的社会改造要求我们
Two beliefs must be established.
必须要建立起两个信仰
That is, the belief in equality and the belief in labor.
即平等的信仰和劳动的信仰
Everyone should be educated.
人人都要受教育
Should work often.
应该常劳动
Always have equal labor in your heart.
心里总要有平等的劳动
And the revolution of labor.
和劳动的革命
Today we talk about transforming society.
我们今天讲改造社会
It is a fundamental transformation of society.
是对社会根本的改造
Not improvement.
而非改良
The so-called transformation of Ben
所谓本的改造
It means when necessary.
是指必要时
We must resort to bloody revolution.
必须要采取流血革命的手段
Of course, we haven't arrived today.
当然 我们今天还没有到
During the bloody revolution.
流血革命的时候
But we always have to have
不过我们总要有
Research methods and beliefs of revolution
研究革命的方法和信仰
It's time for revolution.
到了那个可以革命的时机
We have to fight the devil.
我们非要与那恶魔奋斗不可
good
好
Mr. Chen
陈先生
Come here
过来呀
what's up
怎么了
Mr. Chen is not good.
陈先生 大事不好
We have caused you trouble.
我们给您添麻烦了
What's the trouble
添什么麻烦了
Wuhan authorities heard that Mr. Chen
武汉当局听闻陈先生
Today's talk about socialist ideas
今日所谈社会主义主张
Be appalled
大为惊骇
A circular has been issued.
已发布了通令
Mr. Chen is forbidden to speak.
禁止陈先生演讲
And will expel you from Han.
并要把你驱逐出汉
I came to tell you.
我赶过来给你报信
Please try to leave Wuhan as soon as possible.
请你赶快设法离开武汉
Save yourself from being killed.
免遭毒手啊
I am a scholar by XXL.
我陈某人一介书生
It's a great honor.
实在是不胜荣幸之至
支持陈独秀
支持陈独秀
When will Mom come back?
妈妈 爸爸什么时候回来
It's been a long time.
都出去好久了
Dad will be back soon.
爸爸很快就回来了
Dad will bring you delicious food when he comes back.
爸爸回来的时候给你们带好吃的
Do you miss your father?
你们是不是想爸爸了呀
Of course I miss him.
我当然想他了
Mom misses dad, too.
妈妈也想爸爸了
dad
爸爸
How can you speak of the devil?
怎么说曹操曹操就到啊
What delicious food did you bring me, Dad?
爸爸 你给我带了什么好吃的
sesame candy
麻糖
How's it going? Have you seen Yannian and them?
怎么样 见到延年他们了吗
Hurry up and slow down
紧赶慢赶
Finally, they met before they set off.
总算是在他们出发前见了一面
that's good
那就好
Come into the house
来进屋
Brother Zhongfu is at home, right?
仲甫兄在家吧